John "Jack" Chapel

in john-jack-chapel | ⊕ jackchapel.com | ✓ chapel@usc.edu

Summary

I am an applied microeconomist with a decade of experience conducting social science research in academic and public sector settings. I enjoy collaborating with multidisciplinary teams, working on a diverse portfolio of projects, and implementing causal inference research designs to inform program and policy improvements.

Fields of Specialization: Applied Microeconomics, Health, Labor, Public Policy

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Economics, University of Southern California M.A., Economics, University of Southern California B.S., Economics (with distinction), Tulane University

2019–2024 (expected) 2019–2021 2011–2015

Professional Experience

U.S. Department of Labor, Chief Evaluation Office

Summer Fellow (via Manhattan Strategy Group)

June–August 2023

- Led independent research project on chronic disease and older workers' labor force participation.
- Presented results to Office leadership and a broader DOL audience.

University of Southern California, Schaeffer Center for Health Policy & Economics

Research Assistant for Bryan Tysinger, Director of Health Policy Microsimulation

May 2020–June 2023

- Collaborated with interdisciplinary team to implement dynamic health policy microsimulation models.
- Led the design and analysis for a study projecting future health and economic outcomes and estimating disparities in outcomes between Americans nearing retirement with varying economic status.
- Led the writing and dissemination of the same study, including shepherding the paper through peer review and publishing in *Health Affairs*, multiple presentations at conferences, and giving podcast and press interviews.
- Worked extensively with longitudinal Health and Retirement Study data, interacting with Stata and sensitive datasets through a Linux-based server environment.

University of Southern California, Center for Economic & Social Research

Research Assistant for Silvia H. Barcellos, Associate Professor

May 2022–June 2023

- Collaborated with USC faculty on projects related to the cognition and well-being of a longitudinal sample of older Americans during the COVID-19 pandemic; presented results to CESR staff.
- Conducted statistical analyses including logistic regressions, attrition analyses and data imputation using Stata.

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division for Heart Disease and Stroke Prevention

Research Fellow (via ORISE), Applied Research and Evaluation Branch

June 2015–June 2019

- As economics lead on the Evaluation Team directing national evaluations of federally funded programs/interventions, designed economic evaluations and oversaw contractors performing economic analyses.
- Created data collection tools, built and managed a database that housed national evaluation data reported by state grantees.
- Worked on the Applied Research and Translation team to conduct systematic reviews, policy evidence assessments, and coauthor the Division's seminal Best Practices Guide.
- Collaborated with the Division's Chief Economist on health economics research published in academic journals.
- Developed economic evaluation training materials and instructed practitioners from state/local governments and other public health organizations during in-person and online training sessions and webinars.

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Office on Smoking and Health

Research Fellow (via ORISE), Evaluation and Economics teams

June 2015–June 2019

- With the Office's senior economist, conducted literature reviews, content analyses, and creation of cost data collection tools.
- Reviewed supporting evidence for the 2014 update of the major publication Key Outcome Indicators for Evaluation Comprehensive Tobacco Control Programs.

John "Jack" Chapel 1 Updated: November 21, 2023

ICF International

Intern, Public Health Division

May-August 2012, 2013

• Conducted initial and follow-up interviews with over 100 suicide prevention professionals to support an evaluation of training and referral networks in a federally funded program.

SKILLS

Software: Stata, ArcGIS, Matlab, NVivo, Microsoft Office suite (Word, Excel, Powerpoint)

Programming: Stata, Python, LaTex, Linux, SQL

Graduate coursework: Applied Econometrics for Program & Policy Evaluation, Big Data Econometrics, Health

Economics, Empirical Analysis of Economic Development, Urban Economics, Industrial Organization, Microeconomics, Macroeconomics, Econometrics, Probability & Statistics,

Political Economy (audit), Labor Economics (audit)

Professional Activities

Teaching: CDC DHDSP 2019 Grantee Workshop, CDC DHDSP Evaluation Coffee Break Webinars, CDC

DHDSP 5-Part Webcast on the Basics of Economic Evaluation, Polygence Tutoring

Referee Service: Public Health Nutrition, INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care Organization, Provision, and

Financing

Affiliations: American Society of Health Economists, American Economic Association

Honors & Awards

University of Southern California PhD Academy Scholarship and Research Fund small grant; Dornsife/graduate

school fellowship (2 years)

Centers for Disease Control CDC/ATSDR Honor Award for Excellence in Program or Policy Evaluation

(nominated with coauthors)

Tulane University Cum Laude; Dean's List; annual merit-based scholarship

RESEARCH & PUBLICATIONS

Peer-Reviewed Publications

Chapel JM, Tysinger B, Goldman DP, Rowe JW. The Forgotten Middle: Worsening health and economic trends extend to Americans with Modest Resources Nearing Retirement. *Health Affairs*. 2023;42(9):1230-1240.

Shantharam SS, Mahalingam M, Rasool A, Reynolds JA, Bhuiya AR, Satchell TD, **Chapel JM**, Hawkins NA, Jones CD, Jacob V, Hopkins DP. Systematic Review of Patient Characteristics, Intervention Features, and Cost of Self-Measured Blood Pressure Monitoring Interventions with Support. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2022;62(2):285-298.

MacLeod KE, Chapel JM, McCurdy M, et al. The Implementation Cost of a Safety-Net Hospital Program Addressing Social Needs in Atlanta. *Health Services Research*. 2021;56(3):474-485.

Hawkins NA, Bhuiya A, Shantharam S, **Chapel JM**, et al. A Replicable Approach to Promoting Effective Practices: Translating Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Research. *Journal of Public Health Management and Practice*. 2020;27(2):109-116.

Zhang D, Ritchey M, Park C, Li J, **Chapel J**, Wang G. Association Between Medicaid Coverage and Income Status on Health Care Use and Costs Among Hypertensive Adults After Enactment of the Affordable Care Act. *American Journal of Hypertension*. 2019;32(10):1030-1038.

Chapel JM & Wang G. Understanding Cost Data Collection Tools to Improve Economic Evaluations of Health

Interventions. Stroke and Vascular Neurology. 2019;4(4).

Yarnoff B, Khavjou O, Elmi J, Lowe-Beasley K, Bradley C, Amoozegar J, Wachtmeister D, Tzeng J, Chapel JM, Teixeira-Poit S, The Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program Team. Estimating the Costs of Implementing Components of Stroke Systems of Care and Data-Driven Quality Improvement in the Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program. Preventing Chronic Disease. 2019;16:190061.

Chapel JM, Ritchey MD, Zhang D, Wang G. Prevalence and Medical Costs of Chronic Diseases Among Adult Medicaid Beneficiaries. American Journal of Preventive Medicine. 2017;53(6 Suppl 2):S143-S154.

In-Progress and Working Papers

Distant Friends and Local Public Benefits: Social Spillover Effects from Out-of-State Medicaid Expansions (Job Market Paper)

The Growing Rural-Urban Divide in Older Americans' Healthy Life Expectancy (with Elizabeth Currid-Halkett and Bryan Tysinger) — **Under review**

The Great Migration's Impact on Southern Labor Markets (with Yi-Ju Hung)

Hidden Hypertension and the Labor Force Participation of Older Americans

Does Cognitive Functioning Predict Infectious Disease Risk? Evidence from a Panel of Older Americans Early in the COVID-19 Pandemic (with Sivia Barcellos and Margaret Gatz)

Presentations, Media, and Other Publications

Conferences and Invited Presentations: (* = coauthor, \dagger = poster)

2023: California State University-Long Beach Economics Seminar, USC Applied Microeconomics Seminar, ACAP Social Determinants of Health Learning Collaborative

2022: Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting

2021: International Microsimulation Association World Congress (2)

Academy Health Annual Research Meeting*, Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting* 2020:

2019: American Public Health Association*, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health*, Society for Applied Anthropology Annual Meeting*, Society for Prevention Research Annual Meeting[†]

2018: CDC Evaluation Day

Academy Health Annual Research Meeting[†], Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and 2017:

Implementation in Health*[†], Art & Science of Health Promotion Conference*

QCOR*† 2016:

Media:

Podcasts: A Health Podyssey (September 2023)

Reports: (* = coauthored)

"Economic Evaluation: Intervention Cost Analysis in Public Health" (2018) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"Best Practices for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Programs: A Guide to Effective Health Care System Interventions and Community Programs Linked to Clinical Services" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.*

"What Could Be Addressed in an Evidence-Informed State Workplace Health Promotion Law?" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.*

"The Shands Jacksonville Patient-Centered Medical Home Diabetes and Hypertension Self-Management Education

Model: Program Costs Summary" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"From Policy to Implementation: Collaborative Drug Therapy Management in an Independent Pharmacy" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"Science-in-Brief synopsis of Do State Community Health Worker Laws Align with Best Available Evidence?" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

REFERENCES

Prof. Jeffrey Weaver

University of Southern California

⊠ jbweaver@usc.edu

Prof. Silvia H. Barcellos

University of Southern California

⊠ sbarcell@usc.edu

Prof. Matthew Kahn

University of Southern California

⊠ kahnme@usc.edu

Prof. Bryan Tysinger

University of Southern California

⊠ btysinge@usc.edu